<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ernest Guevarra | Katilingban</title>
    <link>/author/ernest-guevarra/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/ernest-guevarra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Ernest Guevarra</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>©Katilingban `2020`</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 00:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/author/ernest-guevarra/avatar_hu4f9a547149ed73977cb3e5de1c9e7ab2_7097_270x270_fill_q90_lanczos_center.jpeg</url>
      <title>Ernest Guevarra</title>
      <link>/author/ernest-guevarra/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poverty Probability Index</title>
      <link>/post/ppitables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 00:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/ppitables/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;We just launched the eighth release (version 0.5.3) of &lt;code&gt;ppitables&lt;/code&gt;, our &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; package containing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org&#34;&gt;Poverty Probability Index (PPI®)&lt;/a&gt; lookup tables for the 61 countries where &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org&#34;&gt;PPI®&lt;/a&gt; can be calculated. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org&#34;&gt;PPI®&lt;/a&gt; is a poverty measurement tool for organisations and businesses with a mission to serve the poor created by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.poverty-action.org&#34;&gt;Innovations for Poverty Action (IPA)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://katilingban.io/ppitables/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/ppitables.png&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially released in March of 2018, &lt;code&gt;ppitables&lt;/code&gt; has now been downloaded by more than 12,000 &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; users averaging more than 500 downloads per month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed &lt;code&gt;ppitables&lt;/code&gt; to support our use of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org&#34;&gt;PPI®&lt;/a&gt; for surveys and assessments we have conducted. Our main use case for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org&#34;&gt;PPI®&lt;/a&gt; is as an alternative means to classify wealth in our survey sample as opposed to the more widely used and traditional household asset listing and application of &lt;em&gt;principal components analysis (PCA)&lt;/em&gt; for household wealth ranking used by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.worldbank.org&#34;&gt;World Bank&lt;/a&gt; and by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dhsprogram.com&#34;&gt;Demographic and Health Surveys (DHS)&lt;/a&gt;. Using the answers to just 10 questions about a household’s characteristics and asset ownership, a score is calculated and the likelihood of a household living below poverty line is computed. To learn more about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org&#34;&gt;PPI®&lt;/a&gt;, its history and development, go &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org/about-ppi&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. To read more about how to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org&#34;&gt;PPI®&lt;/a&gt;, click &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org/get-started-ppi&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;ppitables&lt;/code&gt; package is aimed at &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org&#34;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; users whose work and/or research includes the use of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org&#34;&gt;PPI®&lt;/a&gt;. The package facilitates the conversion of country-specific household &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.povertyindex.org&#34;&gt;PPI®&lt;/a&gt; score into a poverty likelihood value for a household. Users can immediately write appropriate scripts to convert data they may have of a sample of households in a particular country into the respective poverty probabilities using the country-specific lookup tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this eighth iteration of the package, we have added the most recently released lookup tables for Malawi that uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.poverty-action.org&#34;&gt;IPA&lt;/a&gt;’s current approach to calculating poverty probabilities. For more information about &lt;code&gt;ppitables&lt;/code&gt; and how to use it, visit the package &lt;a href=&#34;https://katilingban.io/ppitables/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. To view the package source code, see the package’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/katilingban/ppitables&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have used &lt;code&gt;ppitables&lt;/code&gt; before or have used it recently, we’d love to hear from you for feedback and comments. If you find a bug or error or would like to request additional feature/s, file an issue &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/katilingban/ppitables/issues&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We are Katilingban</title>
      <link>/post/we-are-katilingban/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/we-are-katilingban/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;katilingban&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;em&gt;[ka-ti-ling-ban]&lt;/em&gt;: (n.) A Cebuano word meaning 1) a group or a community of people; 2) society, organisation or club.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at times of extreme social struggle and difficulty that we are reminded of the &lt;em&gt;primacy of the collective&lt;/em&gt; and the value of working towards the &lt;em&gt;common good&lt;/em&gt;. The current global health crisis brought about by the &lt;strong&gt;COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt; pandemic along with the social upheaval caused by the continuing and persistent racial injustice in the United States recently sparked by the death of George Floyd at the hands of a white police officer and which has grown into a worldwide &lt;strong&gt;Black Lives Matter&lt;/strong&gt; movement are the signs of the times. And these are the times when the power of collective action towards the common good is even more crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is against this backdrop that I, together with three other colleagues, have founded &lt;strong&gt;Katilingban&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;a collective of multi-disciplinary experts and practitioners in public health and nutrition&lt;/em&gt;. Though coming from different nationalities and diverse backgrounds and experiences, one of our main commonalities is our community-based orientation - from a doctor who ran a community-based mental health programme for civil war-affected children and youth in the Philippines, to a public health practitioner who studies and works with communities to understand their context to inform health and nutrition programming, to a community health and nutrition expert who has performed multiple coverage assessments and evaluations of community-based nutrition programmes in the past decade illustrating how the community aspect of these programmes has mostly been poorly done, and to a nutrition data expert who has implemented numerous nutrition surveys to aid in the design and planning of nutrition programmes advocating for more community participation in programme design and planning. And it is this community-based orientation that inspired us to form our own collective, to form &lt;strong&gt;Katilingban&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the remainder of 2020, we would like to once again emphasise the importance of coverage of health and nutrition programming more so in the light of the COVID-19 pandemic. The pandemic has disrupted health and nutrition in more ways than just the infection itself. The global focus on COVID-19 has potentially further widened disparities in other health and nutrition outcomes particularly in low and middle income countries through a variety of mechanisms. We would like to collaborate with other organisations and researchers who are keen on assessing the impact of the pandemic on various aspects of health and nutrition in low and middle income countries. And given the limitations posed by the pandemic, we would like to explore the use of relatively new or less utilised modalities of primary data collection and to test and utilise other analytical techniques on already existing secondary data and routine programme data taht would allow us to still examine and understand the on-going health and nutrition situation other than COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested in collaborating? &lt;a href=&#34;https://katilingban.io/#contact&#34;&gt;Contact&lt;/a&gt; us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
